amgen.com 2019-04-15

# Privacy Statement

### AMGEN PRIVACY STATEMENT

Amgen Inc. and Amgen USA Inc. (collectively " **Amgen** ," " **We** " or " **Our** ") are committed to respecting your privacy. This Privacy Statement is intended to answer your important questions about our privacy practices, whether you are looking for health information or are mining the experience of Amgen to refine your expertise in meeting the needs of your patients.

This Privacy Statement applies to all Amgen online or digital services activities, including, but not limited to [www.amgen.com](http://www.amgen.com/) (the “ **Site** ”), our other websites, mobile applications (“ **Apps** ”) and digital services (“ **Services** ”) in which it is posted or linked.

Please carefully read this Privacy Statement to learn more about how we collect, use, disclose and store information provided and the steps we take to help protect the often sensitive information provided from unauthorized use or disclosure. When you submit information to or through the Services, you consent to the collection, processing and retention of your information as described in this Privacy Statement.

This Privacy Statement is incorporated into and made a part of our Terms of Service. If you have not done so already, please also review Amgen’s Terms of Service. The Terms of Service contain provisions that limit Amgen’s liability to users of the Services.

**IF YOU DO NOT AGREE WITH ANY PART OF THIS PRIVACY STATEMENT, THEN PLEASE DO NOT USE ANY OF THE SERVICES.**

Please note that this Privacy Statement does not apply to information collected through third-party websites or services that you may access through the Services.

Amgen is a multi-national company which maintains datacenters around the world, including the Netherlands and the United States (Amgen Inc.’s global headquarters). Amgen may process personal information in global databases that can be accessed by authorized Amgen personnel worldwide. 

Transfers of personal information among Amgen and its group entities follow applicable laws and our Binding Corporate Rules (BCRs).  For information on the BCRs, please visit <http://www.amgen.com/bcr/>.

#### I. INFORMATION WE COLLECT

When you use the Services, we collect Personal Information and Usage Data.

In this Privacy Statement, “ **Personal Information** " means information associated with or used to identify or contact a specific person. Personal Information includes: (1) contact data (such as e-mail address, telephone number and employer); (2) demographic data (such as gender, date of birth and zip code); and (3) certain Usage Data (defined below).

Certain subsets of Personal Information, such as information about health or medical status (pursuant to all applicable laws) and Location Data (defined below), are characterized as sensitive (collectively, “ **Sensitive Personal Information** ”) and may be subject to stricter regulation and consent requirements than other information. Before providing it to us, we urge you to carefully consider whether to disclose your Sensitive Personal Information. If you do provide Sensitive Personal Information to us, you consent to its use and disclosure for the purposes and in the manner described in this Privacy Statement.

“ **Usage Data** ” is information about an individual’s activity on or through the Services that, by itself, does not identify the individual, such as browser type, operating system and webpages visited.   
We do not consider Usage Data as Personal Information because Usage Data by itself usually does not identify an individual.

If different types of Usage Data and Personal Information are linked together and, once linked, identify an individual person, Usage Data in such limited scenarios may be considered Personal Information.

#### II. HOW INFORMATION IS COLLECTED AND USED

Amgen collects and uses information to operate the Services, including:

**Information That You Voluntarily Provide When Using the Services.**  We collect and use the Personal Information that you voluntarily provide to us through the Services. You may use certain Services without registering or identifying yourself but, if you do not register, you may not have access to all of the Services. If you choose to register, we may use the Personal Information you provide to confirm your registration and to respond to requests from you. Upon your request, we may also use the Personal Information to send you special promotions or newsletters with information that may interest you.

If you are a healthcare professional or an institutional healthcare provider (collectively, “ **Providers** ”), you are responsible for obtaining any legally required authorization, consent or other permission from your patients prior to providing their Personal Information to Amgen through the Services. By submitting any Personal Information about a patient, you represent and warrant to Amgen that you have obtained all required permissions to do so.

**Through Your Use of Interactive Services.**  If you choose to participate in our questionnaires and surveys and other interactive Services, we will collect the information, including health-related information and other Sensitive Personal Information that you share to help us better understand how Amgen products are used in coping with the diseases for which they are marketed.

The information you provide through interactive Services may be combined (subject to all applicable laws) with the Personal Information provided elsewhere in or through the Services. We may combine your and others’ Personal Information to create summary data that we will use for our business purposes, such as research to improve our products and analyses that may help us better market our products.

If you submit health-related Personal Information through the Services to participate in a clinical trial, we may use your Personal Information to assess whether you qualify for enrollment in the trial, to contact you about potential participation in the trial, and to provide you with additional information about the trial.

You may provide information to be published or displayed (" **Posted** ") on public areas of the Services (collectively, " **User Contributions** "). Your User Contributions are Posted and made available publicly at your own risk. Amgen does not control the actions of third parties with access to your User Contributions. If you are a Provider and submit Personal Information about a study subject related to his or her participation in a clinical trial, that Personal Information will be processed in accordance with this Privacy Statement. If we determine that the potential study subject is eligible for the trial, we will use the information to contact you about his or her potential participation in the trial and to provide you with additional information.

**When you Correspond with Amgen about Amgen Products.**  If you contact Amgen or use the Services to ask questions or report problems regarding your experience in using one of our products, we may use the information you provide in submitting reports to the U.S. Food and Drug Administration and as otherwise required of us by law. We also may use the information to contact the prescribing physician to follow up regarding an event involving use of our product.

**Through Data Collection Tools.**   Amgen also automatically collects information about use of the Services through data collection tools, such as web beacons and cookies.

A "web beacon" is a piece of code that enables us to monitor user activity and website traffic. A "cookie" is a randomly-generated unique numeric code stored in the user’s web browser settings or computer’s hard drive. A cookie typically contains the name of the domain (internet location) from which the cookie originated, the “lifetime” of the cookie (i.e., when it expires), as well as the randomly generated unique numeric code.

We use the information collected through data collection tools to monitor usage patterns, store information about user preferences and to improve the Services. For example, your Personal Information may be used to create customized offers, information and services tailored to your interests and preferences.  We may track your activities over time and across third-party websites, apps or other online services to display advertisements on third-party websites. If you do not want us to use your information in this way, please see “Your Privacy Choices” below. For more information about our digital advertising practices, please see “Digital Advertising” below.

**When you Use an Amgen Mobile Application.** When you use an App, we use data collection tools to collect information about your use of and interaction with the App, such as operating system type, browser type, domain and other system settings, search queries, and the time zone in which the mobile device or tablet is located, metadata and other information associated with other files stored on your device.

We also may collect information about the location of the mobile device or tablet used to access the Services (“ **Location Data** ”). Location Data includes: (i) the location of the mobile device or tablet derived from GPS or WiFi use; (ii) the IP address of the mobile device or tablet or internet service used to access the Services; and (iii) other information made available by a user or others that indicates the current or prior location of the user, such as geotag information in photographs.

We will inform you if a specific App or service collects precise Location Data. If you do not want us to collect Location Data from your device, please delete the App or disable the location settings on your device or tablet. Note, however, that disabling the location setting may affect your ability to access and use that App.

**When you Connect with Social Media though the Services:** Certain Services may link with social media platforms and social media plug-ins (e.g., the Facebook "Like" button, "Share to Twitter" button) (collectively, “ **Social Media** ”). When accessing the Services through a Facebook or other Social Media account, Amgen may (depending on the applicable user privacy settings) automatically have access to information provided to or through the Social Media platform. Amgen may collect and use this information for the purposes described in this Privacy Statement or at the time the information was collected.

**Through Service Providers:** Third parties that assist us with our business operations also collect and use information (including Personal Information and Usage Data) through the Services and also may share the collected information with us. For example, our vendors collect and share information with us to analyze use of the Services, to help us detect and prevent fraud and to improve user experience.

#### III. HOW INFORMATION IS SHARED AND DISCLOSED

We may share and disclose information as described at the time information is collected and as follows:

**To Perform Services.** We may use third parties to perform services requested or functions initiated by users. In addition, we may disclose Personal Information to identify a user in connection with communications sent through the Services. We also may offer users the opportunity to share information with friends and other users through the Services.

**With Amgen’s Third Party Contractors.** We share information, including Personal Information, with our service providers to perform the functions for which we engage them, such as data analysis, system design and maintenance, customer services and for marketing and promotions.

**With Co-branding Partners.**  We may partner with other companies to provide you with content or services on a joint or "co-branded" basis. When websites or services are co-branded, you will see both the Amgen logo and the logo of our co-branding partner. When you register for a co-branded website or service, your registration information may be shared with one or more of Amgen's co-branding partners. You may avoid sharing your information with Amgen’s partners on co-branded sites or service by choosing not to use them. Each co-branding partner will have its own privacy policy and its privacy practices may differ from this Privacy Statement.

**Social Media Plugins.** When you use the Services, Social Media operators can place a cookie on your computer to recognize individuals who have previously visited the Services. If you are logged into a Social Media account while using the Services, the social plugins allow that Social Media to receive information that you have accessed and used the Services. The social plugins also allow the Social Media operator to share information about your activities in or through the Services with other Social Media users. For example, Facebook Social Plugins allows Facebook to show your Likes and comments on our pages to your Facebook friends. Facebook Social Plugins also allows you to see your friends' Facebook activity through the Services. Amgen does not control any of the content from the Social Media plugins. For more information about Social Media plugins, please refer to the privacy statements and other legal notices of the Social Media platform.

**Legal Requirements.**  In certain circumstances, Amgen may release your Personal Information in response to a court order, subpoena, search warrant, regulation, binding order of a data protection agency, governmental request or other legal or regulatory process. Amgen may disclose information if we believe disclosure is necessary or appropriate to protect the rights, property, or safety of Amgen and our customers or others.

**Corporate Changes.** We may transfer information, including your Personal Information, in connection with a merger, sale, acquisition, divestiture, restructuring, reorganization, dissolution, bankruptcy or other change of ownership or control by Amgen or any affiliated company (in each case, whether in whole or in part). When one of these events occurs, Amgen will use reasonable efforts to notify users before information is transferred or becomes subject to different privacy practices.

#### IV. DIGITAL ADVERTISING.

We use third-party advertising companies to serve ads on other websites and digital services. These companies may use information obtained from data collection tools in order to measure advertising effectiveness and to provide advertisements of interest to you. 

[**You can opt out here**](http://preferences-mgr.truste.com/?pid=amgen01&aid=amgen_pub01&type=amgen)so as not to receive targeted ads from use of the tools, but this will not affect any general advertisements you may receive.

#### V. LINKS TO OTHER WEBSITES/SERVICES. 

A link to a third-party website or digital service does not mean that Amgen endorses it or the quality or accuracy of information presented on it. If you decide to visit a third-party website or service, you are subject to its privacy practices and not this Privacy Statement. We encourage you to carefully read the privacy policy or statement and other legal notices of each website or service that you visit.

#### VI. OUR CHILDREN’S POLICY

The Services are not intended for use by children. If you are under the age of majority in your place of residence, you may use the Services only with the consent of or under the supervision of your parent or legal guardian. Consistent with the requirements of the Children’s Online Privacy Protection Act (COPPA), if we learn that a child under age 13 has provided Personal Information to or through the Services without first receiving his or her parent’s verified consent, we will use that information only to respond directly to that child (or his or her parent or legal guardian) to inform the child that he or she cannot use the Services and subsequently we will dispose of such Personal Information in accordance with this Privacy Statement.

If you believe Amgen may have any information from or about a child under age 13, please contact our Privacy Office using the contact information at the end of this Privacy Notice.

#### VII. YOUR PRIVACY CHOICES

Amgen aims to provide you with choices regarding the Personal Information you provide to us. This section describes mechanisms that we offer you to control certain uses and disclosures of your information.

When you access any interactive Service, you will be asked to affirmatively choose (" **opt in** ") to provide the requested information. You may always choose not to provide the requested information but then you may not be able to use the Service as intended.

**Correct/Update Personal Information.**  You may correct or update the Personal Information you previously provided to Amgen, by completing the form located at [https://preferences.amgen.com](https://preferences.amgen.com/). 

**Receive Marketing Communications.**  When you register for the Services, you may request to receive email containing information about Amgen that we think you might find useful, including promotions, announcements of new services and products, and newsletters on particular health topics. If you decide, at any time, that you no longer wish to receive these emails you may unsubscribe from our email list by completing the form located at [https://preferences.amgen.com](https://preferences.amgen.com/).

**Accept and Reject Cookies.**  Your browser software can be set to reject all cookies, but if you reject our cookies, certain of the functions and conveniences of the Services may not work properly. To learn more about cookies, please check your browser’s help or similar feature or visit [allaboutcookies.org ](http://allaboutcookies.org/).

**How We Respond to Browser “Do Not Track” Signals.**  Some web browsers incorporate a "do-not-track" or similar feature that signals to websites with which the browser communicates that a visitor does not want to have his/her online activity tracked. If a digital service that responds to a particular DNT signal receives the DNT signal, the browser can block that digital service from collecting certain Personal Information about the browser’s user. As of the Effective Date not all browsers offer a DNT option and DNT signals are not yet uniform. For this reason, Amgen along with many other digital service operators do not currently respond to DNT signals. For more information about DNT signals, visit [allaboutdnt.com ](http://allaboutdnt.com/).

IMPORTANT NOTE: Amgen cannot comply with a consumer's request to amend or remove information that was provided to Amgen by a healthcare professional or a consumer regarding an adverse drug event.

#### VIII. HOW INFORMATION IS RETAINED AND SECURED

We retain information as long as it is necessary and relevant for our operations. In addition, we retain Personal Information to comply with applicable law, prevent fraud, resolve disputes, troubleshoot problems, assist with any investigation, enforce our Terms of Service, and other actions permitted by law. When your Personal Information is no longer needed for Amgen’s business purposes, we dispose of it subject to applicable law.

In accordance with applicable laws, we employ reasonable security measures intended to help protect the security of all information submitted through the Services. The security of information transmitted through the internet cannot, however, be guaranteed. We are not responsible for any interception or interruption of any communications or for changes to or losses of data through the internet. Users of the Services are responsible for maintaining the security of any password, user ID or other form of authentication involved in obtaining access to password protected or secure areas of the Services. Any access to the Services through your user ID and password will be treated as authorized by you. To help protect your Personal Information, we may suspend your use of all or part of the Services, without notice, if Amgen suspects or detects any breach of security. Unauthorized access to such areas is prohibited and may lead to criminal prosecution.

#### IX. CHANGES TO THIS PRIVACY STATEMENT

Amgen reserves the right to change the terms of this Privacy Statement. If we make any material changes to this Privacy Statement, we will notify you in advance through the Services. If we decide to use Personal Information in a manner that is materially different from the uses described in this Privacy Statement or otherwise disclosed to you, you will have the choice to allow or disallow any additional uses or disclosures of your Personal Information. We will not make retroactive changes that reduce your privacy rights unless we are legally required to do so. Your continued use of the Services after the Effective Date constitutes your acceptance of the amended Privacy Statement. The amended Privacy Statement supersedes all previous versions.

#### X. YOUR CALIFORNIA PRIVACY RIGHTS

If you are a California resident under age 18 and are a registered user of any of the Services, then you may request that we remove any of your User Contributions (defined in Section III) you publicly posted on or in the Services. To request removal of your User Contribution, please send a request with a detailed description of the specific User Contribution to the Privacy Office at the contact information below. (You also may be able to log in to your account and delete your own User Contribution.) Amgen reserves the right to request that you provide information that will enable us to confirm that the User Contribution that you want removed was created and posted by you. 

Amgen will make a good faith effort to delete or remove your User Contribution from public view as soon as reasonably practicable. Please note, however, that your request that we delete your User Contribution does not ensure complete or comprehensive removal of your User Contribution. Your User Contribution may remain on backup media, cached or otherwise retained by Amgen for administrative or legal purposes or your User Contribution may remain publicly available if you or someone else has forwarded or re-posted your User Contribution on another website or service prior to its deletion. Amgen may also be required by law to not remove (or allow removal) of your User Contribution.

California Civil Code Section 1798.83 permits individual California residents to request certain information regarding Amgen’s disclosure of personal information to third parties for their direct marketing purposes. To make such a request, please write or send an email to:

Privacy Office  
One Amgen Center Drive  
MS 28-4-A  
Thousand Oaks, California 91320

Be sure to include your name, address, and email address if you want to receive a response by email. Otherwise, we will respond by postal mail within the time required by applicable law.

Effective Date: January 27, 2017

### DECLARACIÓN DE PRIVACIDAD DE AMGEN

Amgen Inc. y Amgen USA Inc. (colectivamente " **Amgen** ," " **Nosotros** " o " **Nuestro** ") se comprometen a respetar su privacidad. Esta Declaración de Privacidad tiene como finalidad responder a sus preguntas importantes sobre nuestras prácticas de privacidad, tanto si está buscando información sobre salud como si está examinando la experiencia de Amgen con el fin de aumentar sus conocimientos especializados sobre cómo satisfacer las necesidades de sus pacientes. Esta Declaración de Privacidad se aplica a todas las actividades de servicios de Amgen en línea o digitales, incluidas, entre otras, [www.amgen.com](http://wwwext.amgen.com/) (“ **Sitio** ”), nuestras otras páginas web, aplicaciones móviles (“ ** _Apps_** ”) y servicios digitales (“ **Servicios** ”) en los que se publica o se crean enlaces.

Lea con atención esta Declaración de Privacidad para entender mejor cómo recabamos, utilizamos, divulgamos y almacenamos la información facilitada, así como sobre las medidas que adoptamos para evitar que esta información, a menudo confidencial, se utilice sin autorización o se divulgue. Cuando se envía información a los Servicios o a través de estos, se está dando autorización para que esta información se recabe, procese y retenga según se describe en esta Declaración de Privacidad.

Esta Declaración de Privacidad está incorporada e incluida en nuestras Condiciones de Servicio. Si aún no lo ha hecho, revise también los Términos de Servicio de Amgen. Los Términos de Servicio contienen disposiciones que limitan la responsabilidad de Amgen frente a los usuarios de los Servicios.

**NO UTILICE NINGUNO DE LOS SERVICIOS SI NO ESTÁ DE ACUERDO CON ALGUNA PARTE DE ESTA DECLARACIÓN DE PRIVACIDAD.**

Tenga en cuenta que esta Declaración de Privacidad no se aplica a la información recabada a través de páginas web o servicios de terceros a los que usted podría acceder a través de los Servicios.

Amgen es una multinacional con centros de datos en países de todo el mundo, entre ellos los Países Bajos y los Estados Unidos (sede central de Amgen Inc.). Amgen puede procesar la información personal que figura en las bases de datos mundiales a las que puede acceder el personal autorizado de Amgen de todo el mundo. 

La transmisión de información personal entre Amgen y las entidades de su grupo cumplen con la legislación vigente y con nuestras Normas Corporativas Vinculantes (NCV).  Para obtener información sobre las NCV, visite http://www.amgen.com/bcr/.

#### I. INFORMACIÓN QUE RECABAMOS

Cuando se utilizan los Servicios, recabamos Información Personal y Datos de Uso.

En esta Declaración de Privacidad, “ **Información Personal** " significa información asociada a una persona determinada, o utilizada para identificar o contactar con esa persona. La Información Personal incluye: (1) datos de contacto (como la dirección de correo electrónico, el número de teléfono y el empleador); (2) datos demográficos (como el sexo, la fecha de nacimiento y el código postal); y (3) determinados Datos de Uso (definidos más abajo).

Determinadas partes de la Información Personal, como la información sobre salud o estado de salud (de conformidad con la legislación vigente) y los Datos de Localización (definidos más abajo), se caracterizan por ser confidenciales (colectivamente, “ **Información Personal Confidencial** ”) y pueden estar sujetas a normativas y requisitos de autorización más estrictos que los de otro tipo de información. Antes de facilitarnos su Información Personal Confidencial, insistimos en que considere detenidamente si quiere hacerlo. Al facilitarnos Información Personal Confidencial, usted autoriza su uso y divulgación para los fines de esta Declaración de Privacidad y de la manera en que está aquí descrito.

Los “ **Datos de Uso** ” consisten en información sobre la actividad de una persona en los Servicios o a través de estos que, por sí sola, no identifique al individuo, como el tipo de navegador, el sistema operativo y las páginas web visitadas. 

Consideramos que los Datos de Uso no constituyen Información Personal porque con dichos datos, por sí solos, normalmente no se puede identificar a una persona.

En ciertas situaciones concretas, como cuando se enlazan distintos tipos de Datos de Uso e Información Personal y, una vez enlazados, se identifica a una persona determinada, los Datos de Uso podrían considerarse Información Personal.

#### II. CÓMO SE RECABA Y SE UTILIZA LA INFORMACIÓN

Con el fin de prestar los Servicios, Amgen recaba y utiliza información, como:

**Información que se facilita voluntariamente cuando se utilizan los Servicios.**  Recabamos y utilizamos la Información Personal que usted nos facilita de manera voluntaria a través de los Servicios. Puede utilizar ciertos Servicios sin registrarse o identificarse, pero si no se registra, es posible que no tenga acceso a todos los Servicios. Si decide registrarse, podríamos utilizar la Información Personal que nos facilite para confirmar su registro y responder a sus consultas. Tras su consulta, también podríamos utilizar la Información Personal para enviarle promociones especiales o boletines con información que pudiera ser de su interés.

Si es usted un profesional sanitario o un proveedor sanitario institucional (colectivamente, “ **Proveedores** ”), antes de facilitar su Información Personal a Amgen a través de los Servicios, tiene la responsabilidad de obtener de sus pacientes toda autorización, consentimiento u otro permiso exigidos por la ley. Al enviar cualquier Información Personal sobre un paciente, usted declara y garantiza a Amgen que ha obtenido todas las autorizaciones necesarias para hacerlo.

**A través del uso que haga de los Servicios Interactivos.**  Si decide participar en nuestros cuestionarios y encuestas, así como otros Servicios interactivos, recabaremos la información, incluida información sobre salud y otra Información Personal Sensible que usted comparta con el fin de ayudarnos a entender cómo los productos de Amgen se utilizan durante el tratamiento de las enfermedades para las que se comercializan.

Sujeto a la legislación aplicable, la información que usted facilite a través de los Servicios interactivos se podría combinar con la Información Personal facilitada en otro sitio en los Servicios o a través de estos. Podríamos combinar su Información Personal con la de otras personas para crear datos resumidos que utilizaremos con fines corporativos, como investigaciones para mejorar nuestros productos y análisis que nos ayuden a comercializar mejor nuestros productos.

Si envía Información Personal sobre salud a través de los Servicios para participar en un ensayo clínico, podríamos utilizar su Información Personal para evaluar si cumple con los requisitos para participar en el ensayo, para contactarle en relación con sus posibilidades de participación en el ensayo y para facilitarle información adicional sobre el ensayo.

Puede facilitar información para que se edite o se muestre (" **Publique** ") en las zonas públicas de los Servicios (colectivamente, " **Contribuciones del Usuario** "). Sus Contribuciones del Usuario son Publicadas y se ponen a disposición del público bajo su propia responsabilidad. Amgen no controla las acciones de terceros que tengan acceso a sus Contribuciones del Usuario. Si es usted un Proveedor y envía Información Personal sobre un participante de un estudio en relación con su participación en un ensayo clínico, esa Información Personal se tratará de conformidad con esta Declaración de Privacidad. Si determinamos que el posible participante de un estudio cumple con los requisitos para participar en el ensayo, utilizaremos la información para contactarle en relación con su posible participación en el ensayo y para facilitarle información adicional.

**Cuando mantiene correspondencia con Amgen sobre los Productos de Amgen.**  Si se pone en contacto con Amgen o utiliza los Servicios para plantear preguntas o para notificar problemas relacionados con su experiencia al utilizar uno de nuestros productos, podríamos utilizar la información facilitada para enviar informes a la U.S. Food and Drug Administration y conforme lo exija la ley. También podríamos utilizar la información para ponernos en contacto con el médico prescriptor con el fin de realizar el seguimiento de un acontecimiento relacionado con el uso de nuestro producto.

**A través de herramientas de recopilación de datos.**   Amgen también recaba de manera automática información sobre el uso de los Servicios mediante herramientas de recopilación de datos, tales como web beacons y _cookies_.

Una "web beacon" es un código que nos permite vigilar la actividad de los usuarios y el tráfico a la página web. Una "cookie" es un código numérico generado aleatoriamente, el cual se almacena en la configuración del navegador web del usuario o en el disco duro del ordenador. Una cookie normalmente contiene el nombre del dominio (ubicación en Internet) a partir del cual esta se originó, el "período de validez" de la cookie (es decir, cuando caduca), así como el código numérico único generado aleatoriamente.

Utilizamos la información reunida mediante las herramientas de recopilación de datos para vigilar las pautas de uso, almacenar información sobre las preferencias de los usuarios y mejorar los Servicios. Por ejemplo, su Información Personal se puede utilizar para crear ofertas personalizadas, así como información y servicios que se adapten a sus intereses y preferencias.  Podríamos realizar un seguimiento de sus actividades a lo largo del tiempo en páginas web de terceros, _apps_ u otros servicios en línea para mostrar anuncios publicitarios en páginas web de terceros. Si no quiere que utilicemos su información de esta manera, consulte "Sus Opciones de Privacidad" más abajo. Para obtener más información sobre nuestras prácticas de publicidad digital, consulte "Publicidad Digital" más abajo.

**Cuando utiliza una aplicación móvil de Amgen.** Cuando usted utiliza un _App_ , nosotros utilizamos herramientas de recopilación de datos para recabar información sobre su uso del _App_ e interacción con este, como el tipo de sistema operativo, tipo de navegador, dominio y otras configuraciones del sistema, consultas de búsqueda y la zona horaria en la que está ubicado el dispositivo móvil o la tableta, los metadatos y cualquier otra información asociada a otros archivos almacenados en su dispositivo.

También recabamos información sobre la localización del dispositivo móvil o la tableta utilizados para acceder a los Servicios (“ **Datos de Localización** ”). Los Datos de Localización incluyen: i) la localización del dispositivo móvil o tableta, obtenida a partir del uso de GPS o WiFi; ii) la dirección de IP del dispositivo móvil o tableta, o servicio de Internet utilizado para acceder a los Servicios; y iii) otra información que el usuario u otras personas hayan facilitado que indique la localización actual o anterior del usuario, tales como información de etiquetas geográficas en fotografías.

Si un _App_ o servicio determinado recabara Datos de Localización precisos, le informaremos de ello. Si no quiere que recabemos Datos de Localización a partir de su dispositivo, elimine el _App_ o deshabilite la configuración de localización de su dispositivo o tableta. Sin embargo, cabe señalar que deshabilitar la configuración de localización puede dificultar su acceso al _App_ y su uso.

**Cuando se conecta con las Redes Sociales a través de los Servicios:** Determinados servicios pueden enlazar a redes sociales y sus _plugins_ (p. ej., el botón de "Me gusta" de Facebook, el botón de "Comparte en Twitter") (colectivamente, “ **Redes Sociales** ”). Al acceder a los Servicios a través de Facebook o cualquier otra cuenta de Redes Sociales, Amgen podría (dependiendo de la configuración de privacidad aplicable) tener acceso de manera automática a información facilitada en las Redes Sociales o a través de estas. Amgen puede recabar y utilizar esta información para los fines descritos en esta Declaración de Privacidad o en el momento en que se recabó la información.

**A través de Proveedores de Servicios:** Las terceras partes que nos ayuden en nuestras operaciones corporativas también recaban y utilizan la información (incluida Información Personal y Datos de Uso) a través de los Servicios y asimismo podrían compartir la información recabada con nosotros. Por ejemplo, nuestros proveedores recaban y comparten información con nosotros para analizar el uso de los Servicios, para ayudarnos a detectar y prevenir el fraude y para mejorar la experiencia del usuario.

#### III. CÓMO SE COMPARTE Y SE DIVULGA LA INFORMACIÓN

En el momento en que la información se recaba, podríamos compartirla y divulgarla según se ha descrito como sigue:

**Para llevar a cabo los Servicios.** Podríamos recurrir a terceros para que lleven a cabo los servicios solicitados o las funciones iniciadas por los usuarios. Además, podríamos divulgar la Información Personal para identificar a un usuario en relación con comunicaciones enviadas a través de los Servicios. También podríamos ofrecer a los usuarios la oportunidad de compartir información con amigos y otros usuarios a través de los Servicios.

**Con terceros contratados por Amgen.** Compartimos la información, incluida Información Personal, con nuestros proveedores de servicios para que desempeñen las funciones para las cuales les contratamos, tales como el análisis de datos, el diseño y el mantenimiento de sistemas, la prestación de servicios al cliente y para marketing y promociones.

**Con socios con los que se comparte la marca.**  Podríamos asociarnos a otras empresas para facilitarle a usted el contenido o los Servicios de manera conjunta o "compartiendo la marca". Cuando en las páginas web o Servicios se comparte la marca, verá tanto el logo de Amgen como el logo de nuestro socio con el que compartimos la marca. Cuando se registre en una página web o servicio en los que se comparte la marca, su información de registro se facilitará a al menos uno de los socios de Amgen con los que compartimos la marca. Puede impedir que su información se facilite a los socios de Amgen en sitios web o servicios en los que se comparte la marca si no los utiliza. Cada socio con el que compartimos la marca tendrá su propia política de privacidad, y sus prácticas de privacidad pueden ser distintas de las de esta Declaración de Privacidad.

**_Plugins_** **de Redes Sociales.** Cuando utiliza los Servicios, los operadores de Redes Sociales pueden situar una _cookie_ en su ordenador para identificar a las personas que previamente han visitado los Servicios. Si tiene iniciada la sesión en una cuenta de Redes Sociales mientras utiliza los Servicios, los _plugins_ sociales permiten que las Redes Sociales reciban la información a la que usted ha accedido y ha utilizado en los Servicios. Los plugins sociales también permiten que el operador de Redes Sociales comparta información sobre sus actividades en los Servicios o a través de estos con otros usuarios de las Redes Sociales. Por ejemplo, los _plugins_ sociales de Facebook permiten que Facebook muestre sus "Me gusta" y sus comentarios en nuestras páginas a nuestros amigos de Facebook. Los _plugins_ sociales de Facebook también le permiten ver la actividad de sus amigos en Facebook a través de los Servicios. Amgen no controla ningún contenido de los _plugins_ de Redes Sociales. Para obtener más información sobre _plugins_ de Redes Sociales, consulte las declaraciones de privacidad y otras notificaciones legales de las Redes Sociales.

**Requisitos legales.**  En determinadas circunstancias, Amgen puede transmitir su Información Personal como consecuencia de una orden judicial, comparecencia, orden de registro, reglamento, pedido vinculante de una agencia de protección de datos, petición gubernamental u otro proceso regulatorio o jurídico. Amgen puede divulgar la información si considera que ello es necesario u oportuno para proteger los derechos, los bienes o la seguridad de Amgen y de nuestros consumidores u otras personas.

**Cambios corporativos.** Podríamos transmitir información, incluida su Información Personal, en el marco de una fusión, compraventa, adquisición, cesión, reestructuración, reorganización, disolución, bancarrota u otro cambio de titularidad o control por parte de Amgen o cualquier filial (en cada caso, ya sea total o parcial). En cualquiera de estos casos, Amgen procurará de manera razonable notificar a los usuarios antes de que la información se transmita o pase a ser objeto de diversas prácticas de privacidad.

#### IV. PUBLICIDAD DIGITAL.

Recurrimos a empresas de publicidad como terceras partes para publicar anuncios en otras páginas web y servicios digitales. Estas empresas podrían utilizar la información obtenida a partir de las herramientas de recopilación de datos con el fin de medir la eficacia de la publicidad y para proporcionar anuncios que sean de interés para usted. 

**[**Puede excluirse aquí**](http://preferences-mgr.truste.com/?pid=amgen01&aid=amgen_pub01&type=amgen)** para no recibir anuncios específicos derivados del uso de las herramientas, y ello no afectará a ninguna publicidad de tipo general que usted pudiera recibir.

#### V. ENLACES A OTROS SERVICIOS Y PÁGINAS WEB. 

Un enlace a una página web o servicio digital de un tercero no significa que Amgen respalde a ese tercero, ni tampoco que respalde la calidad o la veracidad de la información ahí presentada. Si decide visitar la página web o servicio de un tercero, será objeto de sus prácticas de privacidad, y no de las de esta Declaración de Privacidad. Le recomendamos que lea atentamente la política o declaración de privacidad, así como otras notificaciones jurídicas, de todas las páginas web o servicios que visite.

#### VI. NUESTRA POLÍTICA SOBRE MENORES

Los servicios no están destinados a su uso por menores. Si es menor de edad en su lugar de residencia, puede utilizar los Servicios solamente con la autorización, o bajo la supervisión, de su progenitor o tutor legal. De conformidad con la Ley de Protección de la Privacidad Infantil en Internet (COPPA), si llega a nuestro conocimiento que un menor de 13 años ha facilitado Información Personal a los Servicios, o a través de estos, sin la autorización previa verificada de su progenitor, utilizaremos dicha información solo para ponernos en contacto directamente con ese menor (o su progenitor o tutor legal) con el fin de informarle de que no puede utilizar los Servicios, y que a continuación dicha Información Personal se eliminará con arreglo a esta Declaración de Privacidad.

Si cree que Amgen podrían estar en posesión de cualquier información de o sobre un menor de 13 años, póngase en contacto con la Oficina de Privacidad utilizando la información de contacto facilitada al final de este Aviso de Privacidad.

#### VII. SUS OPCIONES DE PRIVACIDAD

Amgen tiene como objetivo aportarle opciones en relación con la Información Personal que nos facilite. En este apartado se describen los mecanismos que ofrecemos para que controle determinados usos y divulgaciones de su información.

Cuando accede a cualquier Servicio interactivo, se le pedirá que seleccione afirmativamente (" **opt in** ") a fin de facilitar la información solicitada. Siempre puede decidir no facilitar la información solicitada, pero entonces no podrá utilizar el Servicio tal y como está concebido.

**Corrección y actualización de la Información Personal.**  Para corregir o actualizar la Información Personal que anteriormente hubiera facilitado a Amgen, cumplimente el formulario ubicado en [https://preferences.amgen.com](https://preferences.amgen.com/). 

**Recepción de comunicaciones de marketing.**  Cuando se registra para utilizar los Servicios, puede solicitar que se le envíen correos electrónicos que contengan información sobre Amgen que creemos podría resultarle útil, que incluirá promociones, anuncios de nuevos servicios y productos, así como boletines informativos sobre determinados temas de salud. Si en cualquier momento decide que ya no desea recibir estos mensajes de correo electrónico, puede darse de baja en nuestra lista de correo electrónico cumplimentando el formulario que se encuentra en [https://preferences.amgen.com](https://preferences.amgen.com/).

**Aceptación y rechazo de _cookies_.** El software de su navegador se puede configurar para que rechace todas las _cookies_ , pero si rechaza las nuestras, algunas de las funciones y amenidades de los Servicios podrían no funcionar correctamente. Para obtener más información sobre las _cookies_ , vea la ayuda de su navegador o una función parecida, o visite [allaboutcookies.org ](http://allaboutcookies.org/).

**Cómo respondemos a las señales de “Do Not Track” del navegador.**  Algunos navegadores incorporan una opción de "do-not-track" o una función similar que indica las páginas web con las que el navegador notifica que un visitante no quiere que su actividad en línea se rastree. Si un servicio digital que responde a una señal determinada de DNT recibe dicha señal de DNT, el navegador puede impedir que ese servicio digital recabe cierta Información Personal sobre el usuario del navegador. A la Fecha de Entrada en Vigor no todos los navegadores ofrecen una opción de DNT y las señales de DNT aún no son uniformes. Por este motivo, Amgen, al igual que otros muchos operadores de servicios digitales, en la actualidad no responde a las señales de DNT.  Para obtener más información sobre señales de DNT, visite [allaboutdnt.com ](http://allaboutdnt.com/).

AVISO IMPORTANTE: Amgen no puede satisfacer la petición de un consumidor de modificar o eliminar la información que un profesional sanitario o un consumidor haya facilitado a Amgen en relación con un acontecimiento adverso relacionado con un fármaco.

#### VIII. CÓMO SE GUARDA Y SE PROTEGE LA INFORMACIÓN

Guardamos la información durante el tiempo necesario y pertinente para nuestras actividades. Además, guardamos la Información Personal para cumplir con la legislación vigente, prevenir el fraude, resolver disputas, solucionar problemas, prestar nuestra asistencia en cualquier investigación, hacer que se cumplan nuestras Condiciones del Servicio y realizar otras actividades permitidas por la ley. Cuando Amgen deja de necesitar su Información Personal para fines corporativos, la eliminamos con sujeción a la legislación vigente.

De conformidad con la legislación vigente, utilizamos medidas de seguridad razonables que tienen como objeto contribuir a proteger la seguridad de toda la información enviada a través de los Servicios. No obstante, la seguridad de la información transmitida a través de Internet no se puede garantizar. No nos hacemos responsables de ninguna intercepción ni interrupción de comunicación, ni de cambios en los datos, o pérdidas de estos, en Internet. Los usuarios de los Servicios son responsables de mantener la seguridad de las contraseñas, identificación de usuario u otra forma de identificación utilizada para obtener el acceso a zonas de los Servicios seguras o protegidas con contraseña. Todo acceso a los Servicios por medio de su identificación de usuario y contraseña se tratará como si usted lo hubiera autorizado. Para contribuir a proteger su Información Personal, si Amgen sospecha o detecta cualquier vulneración de la seguridad, podríamos suspender su uso de los Servicios, ya sea en su totalidad o en parte. El acceso sin autorización a estas zonas está prohibido y puede conllevar una acción penal.

#### IX. MODIFICACIONES A ESTA DECLARACIÓN DE PRIVACIDAD

Amgen se reserva el derecho a modificar las condiciones de esta Declaración de Privacidad. Si realizáramos alguna modificación sustancial a esta Declaración de Privacidad, se lo notificaremos con antelación a través de los Servicios. Si decidiéramos utilizar la Información Personal de manera sustancialmente distinta a los usos descritos en esta Declaración de Privacidad o divulgados a usted de otro modo, tendrá la opción de permitir o prohibir cualquier uso o divulgación adicional de su Información Personal. No realizaremos cambios retroactivos que reduzcan sus derechos de privacidad a menos que la ley exija que lo hagamos. Su uso continuado de los Servicios tras la Fecha de Entrada en Vigor constituye su aceptación de la Declaración de Privacidad modificada. La Declaración de Privacidad modificada reemplaza a las versiones anteriores.

#### X. SUS DERECHOS DE PRIVACIDAD EN CALIFORNIA

Si reside en California, tiene menos de 18 años y es usuario registrado de cualquiera de los Servicios, puede solicitar que eliminemos cualquiera de sus Contribuciones del Usuario (definidas en el apartado III) que haya publicado en los Servicios. Para solicitar la eliminación de su Contribución del Usuario, envíe una solicitud con una descripción pormenorizada de la Contribución del Usuario en cuestión a la Oficina de Privacidad utilizando la información de contacto que figura más abajo. (También podría iniciar una sesión en su cuenta y eliminar su propia Contribución del Usuario). Amgen se reserva el derecho a solicitar que aporte información que nos permita confirmar que fue usted quien creó y publicó la Contribución del Usuario que quiere eliminar. 

Amgen procurará de buena fe borrar o eliminar su Contribución del Usuario del acceso público en cuanto le sea razonablemente posible. No obstante, tenga en cuenta que su solicitud de que borremos su Contribución del Usuario no garantiza su eliminación completa o total. Su Contribución del Usuario puede permanecer en soportes para copias de seguridad, almacenada en caché o de otro modo retenida por Amgen para fines administrativos o jurídicos. Su Contribución del Usuario también podría permanecer en el dominio público si usted u otra persona la han reenviado o vuelto a publicar en otra página web o servicio antes de su eliminación. También es posible que la ley exija que Amgen no elimine (o no permita que se elimine) su Contribución del Usuario.

La sección 1798.83 del Código Civil de California permite que los residentes particulares de California soliciten determinada información en relación con la divulgación por parte de Amgen de la información personal a terceros con fines de marketing directo. Para realizar dicha solicitud, escriba o envíe un correo electrónico a:

_Privacy Office  
One Amgen Center Drive  
MS 28-4-A  
Thousand Oaks, California 91320_ __

Si quiere recibir su respuesta por correo electrónico, asegúrese de incluir su nombre, dirección y dirección de correo electrónico. Si no, le responderemos por correo postal en el plazo exigido por la legislación vigente.

Fecha de Entrada en Vigor: 27 de enero de 2017
